<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/xml/base.min.xml" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ens on </title>
    <link>./en/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ens on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <atom:link href="./en/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>./en/post/</link>
      <guid>./en/post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;thrash-seminars---winter-2021-and-spring-2022&#34;&gt;ThRaSH Seminars - Winter 2021 and Spring 2022&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;about&#34;&gt;About ThRaSH&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Randomized search heuristics such as stochastic gradient methods, simulated annealing, evolutionary algorithms, stochastic neural networks for optimization, ant colony and swarm optimization, and the cross-entropy method are frequently used across many scientific communities. They have been successfully applied in various domains, both for combinatorial and numerical optimization. Despite their success in practice, proving that such algorithms satisfy certain performance guarantees is still a difficult and widely open problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mission of the theory of randomized search heuristics (ThRaSH) seminar series is to contribute to the theoretical understanding of randomized search heuristics, in particular of their computational complexity. The aim is to stimulate interactions within the research field and between people from different disciplines working on randomized algorithms. The primary focus is on discussing recent ideas and detecting challenging topics for future work, rather than on the presentation of final results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steering Committee (Alphabetic order)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lix.polytechnique.fr/Labo/Benjamin.Doerr/&#34;&gt;Benjamin Doerr&lt;/a&gt; (École Polytechnique)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://users.aber.ac.uk/thj10/&#34;&gt;Thomas Jansen&lt;/a&gt; (Aberystwyth University)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.bham.ac.uk/~lehrepk/&#34;&gt;Per Kristian Lehre&lt;/a&gt; (University of Birmingham)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://staffwww.dcs.shef.ac.uk/people/P.Oliveto/&#34;&gt;Pietro S. Oliveto&lt;/a&gt; (University of Sheffield)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imm.dtu.dk/~cawi/&#34;&gt;Carsten Witt&lt;/a&gt; (Technical University of Denmark)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;seminars-winter-2021-and-spring-2022&#34;&gt;Seminars Winter 2021 and Spring 2022&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organisers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://as.inf.ethz.ch/people/members/lenglerj/index.html&#34;&gt;Johannes Lengler&lt;/a&gt; (ETH Zürich)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weijie Zheng (Southern University of Science and Technology)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zoom link for all talks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ethz.zoom.us/j/65881358415?pwd=MHArejFkMmtDSFNNMjUxZTZ2WWNjUT09&#34;&gt;https://ethz.zoom.us/j/65881358415?pwd=MHArejFkMmtDSFNNMjUxZTZ2WWNjUT09&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to holidays and deadlines, this round seminars will be divided into two sessions, Winter 2021 (December 2021) and Spring 2022 (March/April 2022).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;title-tbd&#34;&gt;Title: TBD&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://webia.lip6.fr/~doerr/&#34;&gt;Carola Doerr&lt;/a&gt; (Sorbonne Université)
April 1st 2022, (10:00-11:00 UTC)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;title-tbd-1&#34;&gt;Title: TBD&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hpi.de/friedrich/people/timo-koetzing.html&#34;&gt;Timo Kötzing&lt;/a&gt; (Hasso Plattner Institute)
March 25th 2022, (10:00-11:00 UTC)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;title-tbd-2&#34;&gt;Title: TBD&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.bham.ac.uk/~lehrepk/&#34;&gt;Per Kristian Lehre&lt;/a&gt; (University of Birmingham)
March 18th 2022, (10:00-11:00 UTC)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;simulated-annealing-and-metropolis-algorithm-revisited-in-pseudo-boolean-optimization&#34;&gt;Simulated Annealing and Metropolis Algorithm Revisited in Pseudo-Boolean Optimization&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imm.dtu.dk/~cawi/&#34;&gt;Carsten Witt&lt;/a&gt; (Technical University of Denmark)
December 17th 2021, (10:00-11:00 UTC)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Metropolis Algorithm (MA) and its generalization Simulated Annealing belong to the oldest randomized search heuristics known. Runtime analyses of MA and SA date back to the 1980s and 1990s; however, there are only few recent results on their runtime behavior. We revisit
classical runtime analyses of MA and SA by Wegener (2005) and Jansen and Wegener (2007) and prove partially stronger results using state-of-the-art methods for the analysis. Moreover, we investigate MA on a generalized cliff function, where both the location of the cliff point
and the fitness decline after the cliff can be adjusted, and prove different regimes of runtimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Joint work with with Benjamin Doerr, Taha El Ghazi and Amirhossein Rajabi)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;on-runtime-of-non-elitist-evolutionary-algorithms-optimizing-fitness-functions-with-plateaus&#34;&gt;On runtime of non-elitist evolutionary algorithms optimizing fitness functions with plateaus&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://iitam.omsk.net.ru/~eremeev/index_e.htm&#34;&gt;Anton Eremeev&lt;/a&gt; (Sobolev Institute of Mathematics)
December 10th 2021, (10:00-11:00 UTC)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We consider the expected runtime of evolutionary algorithms (EAs) without elite individuals, based on the bitwise mutation, when they are applied to optimize fitness functions with plateaus of constant fitness. To this end, we consider two types of fitness functions: the Plateau_k function with a plateau of second-best fitness in a ball of radius k around the unique optimum, and the Royal Road function. For the Plateau_k function, we obtain polynomial upper bounds on the expected runtime for some modes of non-elitist EAs based on an unbiased mutation, in particular, the bitwise mutation. This is shown using the level-based theorems. We also note that the EA with fitness-proportionate selection is inefficient for this function, if the bitwise mutation is used with the standard settings of mutation probability. For the Royal Road function, we obtain lower and  upper bounds on the expected runtime, which generalize the previously known bounds for the OneMax function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;a-simple-proof-of-the-general-omegan-log-n-lower-bound-for-mutation-based-evolutionary-algorithms&#34;&gt;A simple proof of the general \(\Omega(n \log n)\) lower bound for mutation-based evolutionary algorithms&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.bham.ac.uk/~jer/&#34;&gt;Jonathan Rowe&lt;/a&gt; (University of Birmingham)
December 3rd 2021, (10:00-11:00 UTC)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent paper by Lehre and Sudholt proved general lower bounds for mutation-based algorithms which use unbiased unary mutation operators. In the special case where mutation is performed bitwise according to some mutation rate, we show that a similar result can be proved rather easily. The emphasis of the Lehre and Sudholt paper is on the effect of the population size, whereas our result shows the effect of the mutation rate. In particular, small mutation rates can lead to stronger lower bounds.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
